[Music]
the finance committee meeting for June
9th,
2025. Uh we have a few resolutions. The
first of which is temporary resolution
54-25, a resolution appointing four of
the initial members to the board of the
Lancaster New Community Authority and
declaring an emergency coming from
economic development committee and uh
Councilman Hope. Thank you. Um I'm not
sure. Are we just discussing names now?
Um maybe the the law director might have
some comments. Sure. Yeah, I got I got a
a list of names and luckily there were
four who weren't going to um have any
conflicts and who were willing to uh
serve the city in this capacity. Um so
I'm going to read those off. I I'm
assuming nobody will have any
objections. Um and then you know if
you'd like you can you can take a vote
on that and make a decision. Um but
first off is Lindy Jackson. I think
everybody's familiar with Lindy, former
service safety director, um serves the
community in a lot of different roles um
and said he'd be willing to serve as one
of the formational board members for the
NCA. And then we have with us tonight
Mr. Jan Kocha who also serves on the
planning commission. Um and Jan was
approached and did indicate that he
would be willing to serve in that
capacity as well. Uh Lisa McKenzie is
the county recorder. Um we have to have
a local government representative and it
can't be somebody that works for the
city of Lancaster. So obviously the
county is the next best choice and Lisa
has volunteered to to take on that role
for us. And then also you all know Matt
Nheiser, former councilman um from the
fifth ward. Matt's currently the city
manager for Baltimore, but he indicated
that he would be willing to serve on the
formational board as well. So those are
the folks those are the names that I got
that didn't have uh conflicts that were
created by their positions on other city
boards or their day jobs or something
like that. Um and I think it's a great
slate of of individuals.
So I that's all I've got. Okay. Thank
you. So
um that's got to be one reading because
of the date. I think we have 45 days
from when we formed it. Yep. Um which
would have put us before the next
committee meeting. Second. My second is
Mrs. Crates. Perfect. Um any comments
from the council? Yay, nay, or whatever.
I ju just for clarification so when
we read that ask for suspension is she
just including the names in that or how
do we want to I'm sorry Anita can just
go ahead and write those in and then it
will be in writing done prior to
council's official meeting and vote. So
she just needs to write them in right
now and then if you all want to you know
make a note on your own legislation
there's no star we'll just do it as
normal. Okay. I left them blank because
I knew they were going to have to be
filled in. So, yep. Thanks. So, in the
event all of a sudden another name pops
up, but what's being presented is the
list of four people. Correct. So, we
would have to vote on those four people
if it happened to be a fifth or sixth
name. I assume that if nobody is
objecting now, I I guess I assumed that
we were going to have this conversation
now rather than during council. If
anybody has an objection, please feel
free to register that. Um, are any of
them going to be here so we can ask some
questions, introduce themselves? Well,
Jan's here obviously. Um, I mentioned
that, but I think we're all familiar
with everybody else. And this was kind
of a lastm minute thing, unfortunately,
because of the timing. So, I don't think
it was really fair to ask any of them to
show up and, you know, put on a a dog
and pony show when we all know that what
their credentials are essentially.
Yep. I just want to clarify that in case
there was a change because you're you're
doing an official slate. So, yep. Good.
Thank you.
Um, next is temporary resolution
55-25, a resolution to authorize the
mayor to enter into a pre-anaxation
agreement with Mark and Beth Powers for
partial number
014112500
04 0 1 01 500
041 0420 0 excuse me and uh 014
401123 0 consisting of
143.319 plus or minus acres in
Greenfield Township and to declare an
emergency uh also coming from economic
development committee Councilman Hoop.
Thank you. Um this is a pre-anexation
um by Rockmill Industrial Park and
Stephanie Bosco is here to
explain why we had no map. and what
exactly was going on. Well, I'm going to
give you guys some background on why
we're proposing to annex this property.
And um I've been in conversation with
Mark Powers for years to try um I know
he's been very interested in selling
this property. This is adjacent to the
Rockmill Industrial Park. So, our plan
has been to market it as advanced
manufacturing. Um and so we were in the
process of um planning this out a little
bit more smoothly, but we have a
prospective user right now. So um this
is a um a a a foreign company that is
coming in to
manufacture oil immersed uh machinery
and equipment for the gas and oil
industry. I'm going to get my notes out
so I say everything properly. Um so they
manufacture transformers that are
commonly used in power distribution and
industrial applications. They are
looking to make $400 million of
investment in North America. They are
looking that phase one is manufacturing.
It'll be two facilities about 27 million
in investment. Um and they are uh
committing to 75 jobs at this point.
um they um they're always very
conservative when they make these
commitments to the state because uh the
state will claw back if necessary. So we
they want to be really conservative, but
we're um they are hoping that um it'll
expand and it'll be over 75 jobs in the
future. So um that was the reason why um
we're moving quickly on annexing this
property. The whole site is 105 acres
and this includes 40 acres that the port
authority owns. So we've been marketing
it together and uh the plan is to make
it advanced manufacturing as it's right
there in the Rockmill Industrial Park.
Um, in terms of what's going on with um,
today's legislation, and I may uh, turn
this over to Stephanie Hall at at some
point, but um, the properties are the
two largest properties that Mark Powers
owns are biseected by the bypass. And so
that has made it a little more
complicated. Um but the county has um
encouraged us to go ahead and submit the
pre-anexation and that um they will help
us um they will they will uh review it
in more depth and uh the plan is to
approve the annexation. Did I get all of
that right, Stephanie? Close.
Yeah, as I said in the email I sent out
today, it's not up to us. None of these
things are up to the city, but the
county has graciously agreed, as
Stephanie said, to look at the
petitioners uh pre-anex or the
petitioner's petition for annexation,
sorry. Um and make a decision about how
they feel this should be um handled. Um
like I said, there are several different
aspects that go into it. And so they're
going to have to sit down and have a
conversation about how they want to to
work those out. Um but we do appreciate
that they're willing to do that um so
quickly. The one thing that's holding it
up is we they have to be able to file
the petition and in order to be able to
file the petition, they ha we have to
have a pre-anexation agreement in place.
So, we're just waiting to get this
pre-anexation agreement done and then
we're going to have the petitioner put
give their petition to the county and
then the county has said that they will,
you know, work on straightening it out
just as quickly as they possibly can um
to allow the the annexation to go
forward.
If anybody has any questions, we're
happy to answer those. We're talking
about 143 acres and this this foreign
entity is going to purchase is looking
to purchase 100 acres. Will that leave
the uh access good access to the
remaining 43 acres for potential future
buyers? Sure. So, it's about 65 on one
side of the bypass and about 65 on the
other side of the bypass. The 65 on the
east side of the bypass, so right in
Rockmill, is adjacent to 40 acres of
Port Authority property. We have
packaged that as 105 acres. Okay.
There's the additional 65 on the other
side which will be available for
additional industrial development. Easy
access from Wilson. Absolutely. Yep.
Good. Yeah. Thanks. Yeah.
Second. Okay. So, that's going to be one
reading and Mr. Wing is going to be my
second. Very good. Thank you, Stephanie.
Good report. Any other questions? I She
walked away, but I think we're
comfortable with this. Moving on to
temporary resolution
56-25, a resolution to appropriate from
the unencumbered balance and amend
certificate of appropriation with the
county auditor and the storm water fund
6006 for payment of compensation time
coming from water pollution control.
Councilman Wayne. Yes. Thank you, Mr.
Chairman. Uh this is actually a pretty
simple resolution. It just increases the
overtime line item in the 60006 fund by
$2,500. I'll let Stephen offer some more
explanation, but it was just uh simply
because a retirement payout was higher
than expected.
Thank you, Councilman. Good evening,
everybody. Um, so yeah, I sent the
email, of course, on Friday with the
long version of the background of this
legislation, but the short version is
that yeah, I had an oversight and just
didn't budget enough or budget the
amount that I typically would to cover
me for an entire year. um once you took
out the um retirement payout for
administrative assistant who retired in
January. And again, just looking to have
that increased to about $2,500 to make
sure we can be covered the rest of the
year if any uh overtime is needed.
Okay.
Um my understanding is we'll we'll do
this for two readings because I think we
have to be compliant with the auditor's
office by the end of the month. and um
Councilwoman Peter will be my second.
Any other questions from council? Very
good. Thank you. Since you're up there,
you might as well stay there. Yeah. and
temporary resolution
57-25, a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding and enter into an
agreement to purchase Timeco model 600
street sweeper from the state
cooperative purchasing program for use
by the storm water and transportation
departments. Again, coming from water
wastewater or water pollution control
committee. Uh, Councilman Wing,
thank you. Uh, again, you got more of
the, uh, detailed specifics on the
Friday email, but, uh, again, for this
one here, we're just looking to replace
our one of our our oldest of the two
sweet street sweepers we have. And, um,
need this legislation in order to do
that. Happy to answer any questions as
usual if uh, anybody has any. Sure. And
you have the funds to purchase this
outright instead of I do. Yes, I have
uh, the funds to purchase this outright.
Uh the previous uh street sweepers we've
um acquired have been through a lease,
but uh instead of paying that off and
the interest on that and having to go
through a lease agreement and all that,
we've uh again I'm able to just purchase
it outright. So that's my plan here.
Yes. And trade in the other one. I think
we're getting 60,000. Correct. Yes.
60,000. And then the remaining funds
that we would owe it would be like
337ish,000 for the uh the new street
sweeper. Okay.
All right. Um, Councilman Als, we may
second. Sure. And then, um, I I believe
there's a limit or there's a time frame
for this quote and getting this in on
time. So, that's Yeah. I was kindly
asking or humbly asking uh two readings
if council would be open to it again
with the reasoning there that um the we
already have we've been told that even
if we were to place the order now, it
would be a nine-month wait. So,
obviously we have a while until we're
going to get the street sweeper, but it
is on a first come first-s serve basis.
So um if in the 3 weeks between what
would be the second reading the third
reading somebody comes in with an order
you know that that wait time could be
pushed back you know weeks or months
depending on on who comes in if anybody
so it's it's possible nobody does come
in but that was the reason why we were
asking for two readings if you would be
willing to do so. Right. Thank you.
Good. Thank you. Any other questions,
comments? Thank you. Thank you all. That
concludes the resolutions. We have no
ordinances this evening. Um, other
discussion items. Departmental updates.
Are you a department?
I am now. Okay. I just wanted to give
all of city council an update on the
city hall restoration or city hall
renovation project where where we are
restoring the exterior of city hall. Uh
we did do our bid opening and we um
Skoolie Caldwell did make make a
recommendation to award the contract to
Tradesman Group. The contract is
5,93,231. So I wanted to make you all
aware of that. That does not include the
elevator. Schoolie Caldwell decided to
bid the elevator separate because it's
two separate types of um
specialties. Specialties. Thank you.
couldn't think of that word. Thank you,
Auditor Nettles. Um, so although we've
awarded the contract for the tradesman's
group, I wanted to let you know we will
still be bidding out the elevator, they
are working on finalizing those specs
and that uh bid should go out here
within the next two to three weeks. So,
Auditor Nettles got the note signed and
we don't we haven't had our meeting yet
with the contractor to actually do um
set all of the dates and the timelines.
Uh, but we should have that shortly and
as soon as I have that, I will be back
with another update for you. So, I'm
open to any questions about city hall.
Appreciate the update. Thank you.
Okay. Any other department, excuse me,
departmental
updates? Tonight's meeting
prep, our new president. That's me. Um,
I just want to clarify, make sure we're
all on the same page on
50 425. So, we discussed four names
earlier. So, if we're voting yes, a yes
vote is for those four names. And a no
vote is you don't like those names. So,
just so we're all on the same page,
right? We don't
not voting for them individually as a
group. Correct. As a group. Okay. It's
as the legislation It's as the
legislation is filled out. I just want
to make sure everybody knows what
they're voting for or who they're voting
for. Yes or no? That's all I had.
Very good. Any other thoughts
uh tonight's meeting or I'm sorry, other
items for finance
committee? I hear there's no need for an
executive session and I would look for a
motion to chair. So moved.
Second. Thank you.
Um all those in favor please signify by
saying I. I. I. And we are adjourned.
Thank you.
Regular meeting of city council will be
at 6:30 on the dock. Thank you.
Great automotive service is just around
the corner at the Buckeye family of
dealerships. Whether it's Buckeye Nissan
and Hillyard, Georgeesville Nissan at
the Georgeesville Auto Mall, Buckeye
Honda of Lancaster, Buckeye Toyota of
Lancaster, or Buckeye Collision Center
in Hillyard. Team Buckeye services all
makes and models at each location,
utilizing modern practices with hundreds
of years of experience, giving you peace
of mind. That's how we
[Music]
Buckeye. The Frankie Smith Funeral Home
and Crematory in Lancaster and the
Johnson Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore
have a long and wonderful history of
serving our community. Feel free to give
us a call at
74-653652. Stop in and see us at either
of our two locations, 405 North Columbus
Street in Lancaster and 207 South Main
Street in Baltimore. Respect for
tradition, regard for change.
[Music]
All right. In the spirit
of gentle reflection, I have something
that if anyone knows what I've been
going through lately, it makes a little
bit of sense, but I think it's good
advice for everyone. So, never take
anything or anyone for granted. Life is
really unpredictable. We can hope,
expect, have visions, but we really
don't have that much of control. So,
just be grateful for everything and
everyone because everything can change
and be taken away in the blink of an
eye. Everything is a blessing. Stay
positive. Be thankful. I'll call
the meeting of Lancaster City Council
order. You join me in the pledge of
allegiance.
I aliance to the flag of the United
States of America and to the republic
for which it stands. One nation under
God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
All right, we call the role, please. Mr.
Als, here. Mr. Bisch, here. Mrs. Kite,
here. Mrs. Hoop.
Mr. Enberg here, Mr. Skunberg here, Mr.
Sully here, Miss Tiner here, Mr. Wing
here, and Mr. Wolfinger here. I'll let
the record reflect that all 10 members
of city council are present.
Reading and disposal of the journal. A
regular meeting minutes dated May 19th,
2025.
Mr. President, I uh or did you have
anything? Nope. Mr. President, I uh
would like have to accept the reading
and disposing of the journal.
Second,
I'm supposed to be the one that's
confused.
It didn't sound like one job. I didn't
know whether it was a motion or not. Did
I do it right? We're doing it right.
We're figuring it out. This is the comic
version of city council meeting, so
we're on the same page. All right. All
right. So, we have a motion and a second
to accept the reading and disposal of
the
journal. Everybody in favor? I.
Anybody not in favor? I'll get it
right. Okay.
Any reports of city officials? I have
email dated May 21st, 2025 regarding E6
bridge rightway acquisition temporary
ordinance 25-25 respond or
um I'm sorry submitted by law director
Stephanie Hall. Email dated May 27, 2025
regarding healthy homes production
grants fund submitted by grant manager
um Michelle McCrady. Email dated May 27,
2025 regarding Lancaster NCA appointing
initial board submitted by law director
Hall. Email dated May 27, 2025
responding to law director Hall on
Lancaster NCA appointing initial board
submitted by Mr. Wolfinger. Email dated
June 3rd, 2025 regarding a public
records request for the city street levy
submitted by President Porter. Email
dated June 4th regarding or 2025
regarding Euing Woods LLC affidavit
notice annexation petition filing
submitted by law director Stephanie
Hall. Email data June 6, 2025 regarding
the 20 June June 26 planning commission
submitted by city planner Chas Carter.
email data June 6, 2025 regarding
background information and legislation
to be introduced to the June 9th uh city
council meeting submitted by storm water
manager Steve Walstead. Email data June
8, 2025 responding to law director Hall
on Lancaster NCA appointing initial
board submitted by Mrs. Hoop. Um and
then a walk-in of um mail June
20 June 9th, 2025 regarding completion
of Sunshine Law submitted by Miss
Tener. And that's it. Mr. President, I'd
like council to um accept the reports of
city officials.
Second. We have a motion and a second to
receive and file the reports of city
officials.
All in favor, please signify by saying
I. I. All oppose, same sign. Motion
carries. Do we have any communications?
I have one. I have mail dated June 6,
2025 regard regarding Langster Carry Out
LLC liquor license
2025001 submitted by Ohio Division of
Liquor Control. Mr. President, I'd like
to make a motion to accept and file
reports of city I'm sorry, of
communications.
Second.
We have a motion and a second to receive
and file all the
communications. All those in favor
signify by saying I. I. All oppose. Same
sign.
Motion carries. Do we have any special
presentations? We have none this
evening.
Have any petitions or memorials? There
are no petitions or memorials.
All right. Now is the time that we set
aside for voters and taxpayers to
address council. There are there any is
anyone here to speak to council this
evening?
Um all right. So we want you to come up
and you do have a clipboard to sign. So
you're just going to state your name and
address and then you have three minutes
uh to address council. Just uh so you
know you've been up here before. We
won't answer any questions at this time.
Um, so feel free. Yeah, my name is Chuck
Burgon. I live at 346 Boowing
Road. And uh, thank you for allowing me
to address the council again. Uh, I want
to bring up it's it's been all over
social media of a couple events that's
potentially happen happening in our city
at I believe it's Double Edge Brewing
and uh, at L City. Uh it's my
understanding that it appears there's
going to be two more drag
shows. Once again, I want to bring to
the attention of the council and the law
director that we do have an ordinance
that prevents these things. And for 40
years, our city has been protected from
lion's den type thing, adult uh strip
clubs and so on. Uh and it's a valid
law. It's still on the books and council
has chose not to modify or change it. Uh
and under
707.05 in this ordinance, it says that
if they want to have a sexually oriented
type thing, they have to file for a
license with the city. And I'm not sure
that that's been done.
Um, so once again, I I I just want
to impress upon the city that we have
laws and if the laws are on the
books, then they're valid and they must
be
uh enforced. Otherwise, it's a
dereliction of your oath of office and
duty. And uh with that, the one thing I
want to leave leave you
with is
uh you know uh the thing of it is
is you know we each have personal
responsibilities and
accountability and if and what I want to
quote is from James
4:17 and what the scripture says is says
therefore to him who knows to do good
and does it
not to him it is sin. And so as
everybody, each of us have to reflect in
our own lives daily, if we see something
that is not right, that is not
wholesome, that does not fall
within what we know is right and wrong,
and we don't do anything about it, then
our silence says that we're sinning.
We're not doing what we're called to do.
So, with that, uh, I'll leave you. And
once again, thank you for allowing me to
speak. Anyone else want to address
council this
evening?
No. All right, we're going to move on.
Do we have any reports of standing
committees? I do. I have six. I have
finance committee meeting minutes dated
May 20th, 2025, submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Safety committee meeting
agenda dated June 5th, 2025. Submitted
by Mr. Bisjack. Safety committee meeting
minutes dated June 6, 2025. Submitted by
Mr. Bisjack. Finance committee agenda
dated June 7th, 2025. Submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Water pollution committee
minutes dated May
29th, 2025 submitted by Mr. Wing. And
then public works committee meeting
minutes dated June 9th, 2025 submitted
by Miss Tiner.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to accept and file the reports of
standing committees. Second.
We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the reports of standing
committees. All in favor, please signify
by saying I. I. I. All oppose. Same
sign.
Motion carries. There any reports of
special committees? There are no
reports. We don't have any public
hearings that I'm aware of. So, we'll
move on to the reading of resolutions.
Starting with temporary resolution 4625,
a resolution to Lancaster's fiscal year
2025 community block grant annual action
plan and statement of objectives to the
authorize to authorize the mayor to
submit the same to the US Department and
Housing and Urban Development. This is
through economic development committee,
Mrs. Hoop and Mr. Skoover.
Mrs. two.
Um, yes, Mr. President, I would like to
make a motion that council pass engross
and honor upon the written record
temporary resolution 46-25.
Second.
Have a first and a second to pass
temporary resolution 4625. Any
discussion? Um, just a quick reminder,
this is to approve the estimated
allocation of about
$488,000 from the CDBG program.
Anyone else?
Call the roll. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Crates, yes. Mrs.
Hoop, yes. Mrs. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Holly Sie, yes. Miss
Tener, yes. Mr. Wing. Yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger. Yes.
Temporary resolution 4625 passes 10 to
zero.
Moving on to the second reading of
resolutions. Starting with temporary
resolution 4925.
A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance. Amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor in the general fund 10001
for the one-time strategic community
investment the grants program and to
declare an emergency. This is through
finance committee Mr. Wolfinger or Mr.
Sully. Mr. Wolfinger a second of three
readings. Second of three readings on
temporary resolution
4925. Uh temporary resolution 5025. A
resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding for a sole source
provider contract for membrane
replacement for the Southwater plant.
This is through water water pollution
committee. Mr. Wing and Miss Teener. Mr.
Wing. This is also the second of three
readings. Second reading on temporary
resolution
5025. Temporary resolution 5325.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance in the 045 police
and fire levy 205 2021 fund
2051 and to amend the certificate of
appropriations with the Fairfo County
auditor and to declare an emergency.
This is through finance committee Mr.
Wolfinger and Mr. Als. Mr. Wolfinger.
Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that council spend its
rules and waves a third readings of
temporary
resolution 53-25.
Second.
Excuse me. We have a motion and a second
to suspend our rules and wave the third
reading at temporary resolution 5325.
Discussion.
No discussion. No. Call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bisch. Yes. Mr. Crates.
Yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Lockenberg,
yes. Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes.
Miss Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes.
Motion to suspend passes 10 to zero.
Mr. Wolfinger. Yes. Um, I'd like to make
a Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon a written record temporary
resolution 53-25.
Second. We have a motion and a second to
pass and engross and upon the written
record temporary resolution
5325. Discussion. Yes, there is. Please.
Uh, this resolution authorizes surface
safety director to
um enter into contract for
$660,000 and account for contingencies
for the fire department's building on
East Main Street engine house number
two. Three. Thank you. Anyone have any
other discussion? Tener. Yes. I want to
do a little bit of background
history. Um, in February 2nd of 2024,
um, we had a a meeting, our safety
meeting, and uh, we were talking about
medics at that, I'll say squads because
when you think of medics, I guess that's
people, but a squad. And uh I asked the
question, how
many squads have we had since I've been
on council since so since 2016 we have
had four new squads. We were told at
that meeting and I I will read what um
Mr. Bischek wrote in the minutes. As far
as vehicles go for medics three and four
are anticipated to deliver to be
delivered in late summer, early fall.
So, mind you, this is 2024 and there
will be a need for legislation to budget
for a new truck for Medic 2. Now, uh I
remember at that meeting looking at Mr.
Bischeck when they listed the amount of
emergency squads that we had had since
2016 and I said to him, "Put that in the
minutes." And then he let let us
know. And then I said, "You know, I
missed that uh with reading minutes. I
noticed something that was left out,
unless I missed it. Um, Lang Fire
Department received one new medic in
2016, one medic in 2019, and two in 2023
in a new fire truck during COVID. And
Mr. Bischek says, well, he says, "Thank
you. I only wanted to note new items and
we received recently or received soon.
That being said, I appreciate the
input." So, that was never amended. So,
are you guys wanting new squads? You
guys want to build a building over a
half a million dollars to maintain
vehicles and these are pretty new
vehicles and you want a new firehouse
because um Carrie Woody, you know, we're
looking at the on Ed Road and that. So,
are we getting new squads too? Are you
guys wanting new ones on top of the
building? There's I think a few
questions there. One of it's what
question do you have about the the
building behind engine house 3?
Well, I mean, if you you've got new I
mean, the are they warrantied? I mean, I
I don't you guys want to build a
building for half a million dollars, but
it also says here for last year in the
minutes that um early summer or fall of
last year, there will be a need for
legisl Oh, that's a truck. Uh medics
three and four anticipated to be
delivered in late summer or early fall.
And this is last year, 2024.
Correct. So, the status of our fleet of
EMS units, our frontline units, medic
one is a 2016. I anticipate delivery in
the next two months. Um, it is being
replaced. It was the most recent one
that we ordered. Um, medics one, I'm
sorry, medics four and three were
replaced in uh 2023. So, they're 2022
and a 2023 model. Um, medic 2 serving
the west side is a 2019 model. Um and
it's coming upon um our goal is to
replace them at roughly 16,000 engine
hours, which is kind of the equivalent
of 500,000 miles. Um that truck being on
the farthest part of town um tends to
put more hours on the engine. All three
stations average a different number of
hours every year. So, um to put in
perspective, right now I don't have a
spare fire truck or a spare medic
because they're both in service. My um
reserve engine is having a head gasket
replaced. Um, Medic one is having an
alternator replaced. So, I don't have a
medic five right now and I wouldn't have
an engine one to put in service because
it's already being used as other
frontline trucks are being maintained.
The building we're requesting would
consolidate all those resources into one
area um for more quick deployment um in
a a place that's more conducive for
storage of our fire apparatus um and
giving us the facilities and the means
to work on the trucks ourselves which
we've done um I think consistently what
we can do in house for years saving the
city quite a bit of
money. Anyone else? I have a question.
Yes. Um, since you're up there,
um, with this
building, can you as a fire department,
because we are paying you for an
ondemand service, can you provide the
city of Lancaster a better service with
the building being there? Yes. This
improves our response capabilities.
Okay. Thank you.
Anyone else? I I would just say I I was
involved in fleet maintenance for a
number of years and I would just say
that I don't care how new the equipment
is. You you have to have a place to to
work on equipment. You have to keep your
equipment up. I've seen brand new
equipment break down and the fact that
they want to do it and and they and they
have the capability to do it. We need to
give them a place to do it. But I think
that that's reasonable. Sorry. I also
asked it to scale even half even I even
I mean threw that out there you know
because instead of four bays could you
have two to scale it down and that
immediately no I mean didn't even look
into that I I believe I answered that
question and yes the building will be
full at the end of 2026 with the reserve
EMS units and the reserve fire apparatus
and the new smoke all I anticipate all
four bays to already be full by the end
of 2026.
I would like to have this put into
um record.
Any other discussion on this
piece? No. So I will ask for roll call
on the motion to pass. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kates, yes. Mrs.
Hoop, yes. Mr. Locktoberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tiner, no. Mr. Wing, yes. Mr. Mr.
Wolfinger. Yes. All right.
Motion passes 9 to
one. All for second reading resolutions.
We're going to move on to first readings
with temporary resolution 5425.
a resolution appointing four of the
initial members to the board of the
Lancaster New Community Authority and
declare an emergency. This is through
economic development committee, Mrs.
Hoop and Mrs. Kra.
H.
Um, yes, Mr. President. I would like to
make a motion that council pass and grow
Senator upon the written record
temporary resolution.
What? is suspended.
Oh, shucks. Sorry. My bad. Scratch that.
I was doing something else myself. So, I
didn't even know you messed up. So, what
do we shame on you? Um, no, we need to
suspend. So, I would like to make make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 5425. Second. We
have a motion in a second to suspend the
rules and wave the second and third
reading. discussion.
No. No. Please call the role. Mr. Als,
yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kit, yes.
Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes.
Motion carries 10 to zero. M. Soup. Now
I would like to make a motion that
council pass in gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
54-25.
Second.
We have a motion and a second to pass
temporary resolution 5425. Discussion.
No, this is just well yeah I guess this
is just to appoint the four people to
the um NCA and that was the four that we
discussed in finance.
Any other discussion questions? Should
we read the names? I can do that. I have
for the citizen members, um, Matt
Nighheiser, Lindy Jackson, Jan Kosha,
um, and then local government member
would be Lisa McKenzie. Thank you.
Any other discussion,
questions? Motion. We have a motion to
pass. Please call the role. Mr. Als,
yes. Mr. Bischeck, yes. Mrs. Kra, yes.
Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Luenberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes.
Temporary resolution 5425 passes with a
vote of 10 to zero. Temporary resolution
5525.
A resolution to authorize the mayor to
enter into a pre-anexation agreement
with Mark and Beth Powers of Parcel
numbers 014
0112500
010 500
014 01 0420 0 and 014
0112300 0 consisting of
143.319 plus or minus acres in
Greenville Township and to declare an
emergency. This is through economic
development committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Wing. Mrs. Hoop. Yes. I would like, Mr.
President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the second and third readings of
temporary resolution 55-25.
Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
third readings of temporary resolution
5525. Any discussion? Um we talked about
death isn't finance um but this is just
to enter into a pre-anexation
agreement for the
um land in Greenfield Township. Okay.
Any other discussion?
Call the role. Mr. Als. Yes. Mr.
Bisjack. Yes. Mrs. Kitz. Yes. Mrs. Hoop.
Yes. Mr. Lockberg. Yes. Mr. Skunover.
Yes. Mr. Sully. Yes. Miss Teener. Yes.
Mr. Wing. Yes. And Mr. Wolfinger? Yes.
Motion to suspend passes 10 to zero. M.
Um. Yeah. I'd like to make a motion that
council pass engross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
55-25.
Second. Have a motion and a second to
pass temporary resolution
5525. Any additional discussion? Any
questions? Anyone?
Seeing none, please call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kes,
yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Luenberg? Yes.
Mr. Scooter? Yes. Mr. Sully? Yes. Miss
Ter? Yes. Mr. Wing? Yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger? Yes. Temporary resolution
5525 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 5625.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor auditor in the storm
water fund
6006 for payment of compensity
compensate compensary time water
pollution committee Mr. Wing and Mr.
Miss Tener Mr. wing. Yes, this is the
first of two readings. First of two
readings on temporary resolution
5625. Temporary resolution 5725. A
resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with the
competitive bidding and enter into an
agreement to purchase a Thai MCO model
600 street sweeper from the state
cooperative purchasing
program for use by the storm water and
transportation departments. This is
through water water pollution committee.
Mr. Wing and Mr. Als Mr. Wing this is
also the second of three excuse me first
of two readings. First of two readings
on temporary resolution
5725. Do we have any other resolutions
to come before
council? Seeing none, we'll move on to
ordinances with the third reading of
temporary ordinance 2525.
An ordinance to authorize the mayor to
acquire the permanent and temporary
rideway necessary for the East 6th
Avenue Bridge over Feder's Run
replacement project. This is through
public works committee, Miss Tener and
Mr. Luenberg. Miss Tiner, Miss um I can
make the motion to replace first. Okay,
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to replace temporary ordinance 2525 with
temporary ordinance 2525 star. Second.
We have a motion and a second to replace
temporary ordinance 2525 with the
amended 2525 star. Discussion. Not this
time.
Any other? Seeing none, please call the
role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes.
Mrs. Kra, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr.
Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Scooter, yes. Mr.
Sully, yes. Miss Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing,
yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes. Motion to
replace with star version passes 10 to
zero. Miss Tiner. Mr. President, I'd
like to make a motion that council
passing and gross and enter upon the
temporary record, the temporary
ordinance 2525 star.
Second. A motion
to
pass temporary ordinance 2525 star.
Discussion. Yes. This was just for a
grant and there was a sentence that was
missing out of the grant uh request. So,
it's just a housekeeping item. They're
putting a sentence in so we can
hopefully um get the grant which looks
like we
will. That right? Am I reading the wrong
thing?
Um this this piece uh there is money as
Councilwoman Tiner was saying, but uh
the money needs to be spent on rightway
and easement for the uh East 6th Avenue
bridge replacement. Um and so this
version uh creates or gives the
emergency language that's required in
order to uh use that money faster in the
process of easement and right-of-way
acquisition.
All right. Sorry, Miss Tina. The grant
thing threw me off. Yeah, sorry about
that. That's all right. Uh, any other
discussion? Seeing none, please call the
role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bizjack, yes.
Mrs. Kites, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr.
Locktoberg, yes. Mr. Screenover, yes.
Mr. Sully, yes. Miss Ter, yes. Mr. Wing,
yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes.
Temporary ordinance 2525 star passes 10
to zero.
Moving on to the second reading of
temporary ordinance 2625,
an ordinance to accept a petition for
the annexation of
point 605 plus or minus acres in the
Pleasant Township and to consent the an
annexation and to declare an emergency.
This is through economic development
committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kates.
Mrs. Who? This is second of three
readings. Second of three readings on
temporary ordinance
2625. No first readings of ordinances.
Do we have any other ordinances to come
before council?
No sir. Seeing none. I don't see any
tabled
legislation. Do we have any unfinished
business? Anyone any new business anyone
wants to discuss? I would like to know
Stephanie if you could answer Mr. Beun's
question regarding the uh events that
are possibly going to go on at L City
and Double Edge. Do they need permitting
or is it already done or I don't know to
be honest. Um I haven't heard about
either of these events. So I don't know
anything about them. If there are
permits to be that would be required um
those come through the service safety
director's office. I I haven't seen
anything with regard to either of those
events. I get a copy as soon as um
they're filed with the service safety
director. So I can't speak to those
unfortunately. Okay. I was just getting
and and Carrie, you haven't seen any I
will just echo that my office isn't
aware of either of those events either.
Thank you.
Anyone else before I read these two
other pieces or ask you to read those
two pieces? I have I have new business.
I have um there will be a public hearing
on the Euing Woods LLC zoning map
amendment on July 14th,
2025. And then I also have that I
received two notifications from the Ohio
Division of Liquor Control for Lancaster
Carry Out LLC permit number 501283.
Mr. President, can I address those
please? Yep. So, the communications uh
that were received were the standard
letter and then new permit notification
that we receive whenever there's a new
permit issued within the city limits. Um
when there is a new permit, the
Lancaster Police Department gets
information um sensitive information
with regard to the ownership of that
permit. Um unfortunately, it did not get
to LPD. So, LPD was unable to share that
with me. Um, I reached out to the
Division of Liquor Control and they're
going to resend that, but they couldn't
resend it in time for tonight's meeting.
Um, so I would ask that somebody make a
motion and that you all vote to delegate
your ability to object to that new
permit to the mayor. Um, and I'm I'm
doing that because um, you know,
typically there's no action that you
need to take. Um, you know, we we rely
on what the police department tells us
in terms of what is happened at a
business. Um, but this business has
absolutely no no background right at the
location that they're about to have a
permit. And for you of those of you who
don't know, it's the um Lucky Shots Putt
Putt is the listed address out on East
Main Street across the street there from
Wendy's and Dairy Queen. Um, you know,
just want to take a look at um what kind
of business is going to be there, what's
going to happen, how that's going to
affect, you know, everything in the
surrounding community. And again, we
don't typically object to these,
especially new ones, but it's always a
good idea to know who is going to be
running that business and whether or not
there's any kind of criminal history
that we should be aware of. Um, so I
would just ask you to delegate that
authority to the mayor because they they
said they can't have the information to
us before the 23rd, which would give me
time to formulate a response whether you
know to object or accept um depending on
what that information says.
So, we're looking for a motion. Yes. A
motion to de delegate your authority to
the mayor with regard to the new liquor
permit.
Anyone? So moved. Thank you. Thank you.
I'll second that. Okay. So we have a
motion and a second to delegate our
authority to the mayor on this
particular matter.
You don't need to do a roll call. Yeah.
Voice vote will suffice. All those in
favor signify by saying I. I. I. I. Same
sign. No motion carries. Thank you.
You're welcome. Any additional new
business, Miss Tiner? Yes. Uh this
coming Saturday, uh June 14th from 9:00
a.m. to 3:00 p.m. downtown, uh there's
going to be a flag day event. Um there
will be um proclam proclamation red
historic speeches
reenactments flag etiquette kines
freedom never free be there food vendors
and there's several sponsors churches
businesses and private individuals
Vietnam vets and vets American Legion
and veterans of foreign wars. So
everybody's invited to come downtown
Saturday from 9 to 3 and celebrate our
flag. Perfect. Thank you. Anyone
else ask the Mr. President? Yes, ma'am.
Because Becky brought it up, I will say
in preparation for Flag Day, we are
going to be setting out a bunch of small
flags along the sidewalk in the city's
uh property this coming Wednesday
afternoon at around 3 p.m. So, if anyone
is available and would like to help us
set out about 100 flags, you are more
than welcome to join us. And everybody
pray that it stops raining at some point
in time this year. We're in Ohio. We can
handle it now.
Ridiculous. Okay. Uh announcing the
scheduled meetings, please. Um next
regular meetings um for council is June
23rd, 2025 at 6:30 p.m. and ch council
chambers and then July 14th, 2025 at
6:30 p.m. in council chambers.
No special meetings scheduled, I see.
And how about regularly scheduled
committee meetings, please? I have
public works committee July 11th at 7:30
a.m. City Hall 1897 conference room.
Service committee um June 13th at 8 a.m.
City Hall 1897's conference room. And
then water water pollution control
service committee June 13th at 9:00 a.m.
July I mean I'm sorry city hall 1897
conference room. Thank you. Uh reading
of bills. I have one for MNCO and it's
$123.84.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to pay the bills. Second. Have a motion
and a second to pay the bills. All in
favor, please signify by saying I. I.
All oppose, same sign. Motion
carries. You can pay the bill. We have
no need for executive session that I am
aware of. And before I ask for a motion
to adjurnn.
Thank you for your patience. And we made
it through and nothing caught on fire.
So motion to adjourn. Mr. President, I'd
like to make a motion to adjurnn.
Second.
Motion and second to journ. All in
favor? I. We are adjourned. Thanks for
coming everyone.
That was 37.
[Music]